Finding aid for Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (University of Michigan) records, 1966-2010 (bulk 1970-1994)
Bentley Historical Library
Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (University of Michigan) records
1966-2010
1970-1994
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Department of Afroamerican and African Studies.
2012140 BImu C26 2, FImu C26 outsize
54.5 linear feet
1 oversize folder
1.9 TB
This record group pertains to the University of Michigan Department of Afroamerican and African Studies and to campus, regional, and national organizations devoted to political and civil rights causes from the 1960s to the 1990s. The collection includes print documents, photographs, and audio-visual material that document racial harassment incidents, political protests, scholarly conferences and symposia, MLK Day celebrations and black student life on the U-M campus. There are also materials about the civil rights movement of the 1960s and the anti-apartheid and divestment movements of the 1980s. Originally a Center, the unit was formally recognized as a department of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts in 2011.
The record group (donor no. 10110 ) was received from the unit in May and November of 2011 and June and July of 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy as noted in this finding aid.
The entire DAAS collection has been digitized; digital versions of the original records may be accessed from the campus of the University of Michigan and also remotely by faculty, students, and staff with valid credentials.
The DAAS record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 26
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
The University of Michigan Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (DAAS), was founded in 1970 as Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (CAAS) to be a home for interdisciplinary research, teaching and community outreach. In 2011, CAAS became the Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (DAAS) in the College of Literature Science and the Arts (LSA).
CAAS's beginnings are rooted in the era of the modern civil rights and black consciousness movements of the 1960s. Beginning in 1968, following the assassination of Martin Luther King, black students commandeered several campus buildings and demanded talks with new University President Robben Fleming. In addition to discussing the overall atmosphere on campus for black students, the activists voiced the first public call for a program in Black studies. A committee was charged by Rackham Dean Stephen H. Spurr to explore the possibility of creating an African-American studies program. Interest in such a program increased in 1970, when participants in the first Black Action Movement (BAM) on campus called for the establishment of a "Center for Afro-American Studies" to be based on a proposal written by J. Frank Yates, Assistant to the Dean of LSA.
When the Regents established the center in the summer of 1970, its scope was broadened to include African studies, on the expectation that, "the study of Africa, Afroamerica, and the Caribbean within a single intellectual framework was not only defensible but represented the future direction of Black Studies." This "diasporic perspective" has defined the framework for study and teaching conducted by the center's faculty. The center was to offer an interdisciplinary curriculum taught by an international faculty and had a first-year enrollment of 1,026 students. Over the next two years the center acquired a "Writer in Residence" program and a visiting faculty program. CAAS faculty and students envisioned a commitment to both the University and the local and regional Black communities and over the next few years, center participants worked to find the right balance between these activities.
The Ford Foundation granted CAAS funds for the project "From Margin to Center: Towards a New Black Scholarship," beginning in 1988 and additional funds for its pilot project "Strengthening African Studies." The program provided: a small seed grant program to foster collaborative research on Africa; helped fund a Summer Institute on Social Science Methods and African Studies; and an Africa Theme Semester.
During its forty-year span CAAS has played host to a number of notable events and programs, including an ongoing colloquium series, the Dubois-Mandela-Rodney Fellowship Program (since 1988), and two conferences in memory of the noted poet and essayist Robert Hayden in 1980 and 1990. The center has also sponsored study abroad programs in Barbados, Jamaica, Ghana and South Africa. Since 2000, CAAS has also been the home of the South African Initiatives Office (SAIO).
Originally, the Center sponsored an undergraduate concentration. An undergraduate minor was added in 2000 and a graduate certificate program began in 2005. First housed on Monroe Street, CAAS moved to West Hall and then to its current home in Haven Hall. Facilities have included a professionally staffed library and archives and an art gallery.
The Lemuel A. Johnson Library at CAAS supported the curriculum by collecting and organizing archival materials related to black faculty, staff and student organizations, student activism, and national and international events relevant social justice. These files, now transferred to the Bentley, were publicly available for research and consultation. They included records relating to the BAM movements as well as several other university organizations, whose records were transferred together with the CAAS organizational archives. Brief profiles of those documented organizations follow.
The Black Action Movement (BAM) was formed in 1970 from a coalition of the Black Student Union, the Black Law Students Association, the Association of Black Social Work Students, and groups of black students from the Medical School and the Psychology Department. They presented a list of demands to then University President, Robben Flemming. One of those demands, was, in fact the establishment of CAAS. There were two subsequent BAM episodes, BAM II (1974-5) and BAM III in 1985-7.
The United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR) formed in the Spring of 1987 in response to a series of racist incidents on campus, including racist jokes aired on a campus radio station and a racist flyer pushed under the door of black women studying in a dormitory lounge. UCAR engaged in action aimed at U-M administrators, putting forth demands for institutional changes and convening mass protests in response to racist incidents. In addition it presented teach-ins and speakers. Originally funded by the Office of Minority Affairs (created in response to an original UCAR demand) for specific projects, other funds were provided by the organization's own fundraising and the Michigan Student Assembly.
UCAR also founded the Ella Baker-Nelson Mandela Center for Anti-Racist Education, or the Baker-Mandela Center (BMC) during the summer of 1988. Its purpose was to collect and generate literature, provide a speakers bureau, and to serve as a gathering place for anti-racist activists. The overall objectives were to promote anti-racist consciousness and to promote anti-racist student leaders, particularly within Third World communities; to heighten the level of discussion and research on various aspects of race, class and gender issues and to provide concrete tools to anti-racist organizers to help refute stereotypes and myths, and challenge apathy or cynicism. It was housed in the East Engineering Building. Barbara Ransby and Tracye Matthews were important leaders in the organization of the center.
The University of Michigan Free South Africa Coordinating Committee (FSACC) was a diverse campus-based group of faculty and students opposed to the Apartheid system in South Africa, founded in the Spring of 1985. The group's aims included producing literature, sponsoring events and pressuring institutions to sever economic ties with corporations doing business in South Africa. FSACC records concern activism during the 1980s and early 1990s, especially the construction of an "anti-apartheid shanty" on the University of Michigan Diag and a petition to grant Nelson Mandela an honorary degree.
The Students of Color Coalition (SCC), another campus-based group, formed to protest the mocking use of Native American names, images and regalia by a semi-secret student honor society called Michigamua. In early 2000, SCC members occupied the Michigamua offices in the tower of the Michigan Union for thirty-seven days. As a result of the controversy, Michigamua agreed to stop using Native American practices, and in 2006 adopted a new name, "The Order of Angell."
Directors of the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies
1970 Acklyn Lynch
1970-1971 (Acting) J. Frank Yates
1972-1973 Harold W. Cruse
1973 Leslie Owens
1973-1978 Ozzie Edwards
1978-1981 Ali Mazrui
1981-1984 Niara Sudarkasa
Fall 1982 (Acting) 1984-1986 Thomas C. Holt
1986-1990 Lemuel A. Johnson
1990-1993 Earl Lewis
1993-1996 Michael Awkward
1996-1998 Sharon F. Patton
1998-2005 James S. Jackson
2005-2010 Kevin Gaines
2010-2011 Angela D. Dillard
Chair of the Department of Afroamerican and African Studies
2011-2014 Tiya Miles
2014-2018 Frieda Ekotto
2018- Matthew J. Countryman
------------------
1. History of the Center and Program, CAAS organizational archives, Box 16
Summary Contents List
Black student activism -- Boxes 1-5 and 55
Black Action Movements -- Boxes 1-2 and 55
Other activism -- Boxes 2-5
Blacks at U-M -- Boxes 6-10
CAAS organizational archives -- Boxes 10-27
Media -- Boxes 28-54
Audio recordings on cassette -- digital copies available for use in the reading room -- Boxes 28-36
U-Matic videotapes -- Boxes 37-45, 52
VHS videotapes -- Boxes 46-52
Other media -- Boxes 53-54
The records of the Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (DAAS; formerly known as the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies, or CAAS) include correspondence, syllabi, clippings, publicity materials, photographs and audio and video recordings of campus speakers. The record group includes archival material that was originally collected and made available in DAAS's library relating to black activism and to organizations of interest to black students, faculty and staff, as well as DAAS's own organizational archives. Because these materials have been consulted and cited by researchers prior to their transfer to the Bentley in 2011, their original arrangement has been preserved so far as possible.
Paper and photographic records consist of three major series: Black student activism, 1969-2001 (5.5 linear feet), Blacks at U-M, 1969-2007 (4.5 linear feet) and Organizational archives of CAAS, 1962-2010 (17 linear feet) (formerly designated simply "Archives.") There is some overlap of subject matter. These categories reflect the organization of the materials imposed by CAAS librarians and archivists prior to transfer to the Bentley in 2011.
The following list identifies the greatest concentration of material relevant to some of the notable subjects in the collection:
The Black Action Movements (Boxes 1-2 and 55)
Incidents of on-campus harassment and responses (Boxes 1, 2, 4)
South Africa, apartheid, and divestment -- (Boxes 2, 3, 5)
Free South Africa Coordinating Committee (Box 3)
Washtenaw County Coalition Against Apartheid (Box 5)
United Coalition Against Racism and the Baker-Mandela Center (Boxes 1, 4, 5)
The Michigamua controversy (Box 3)
The Nelson Mandela Honorary Degree Petition (Boxes 3, 11)
Gulf War activism (Boxes 3, 4)
This record group also includes a large number of audio and video recordings of presentations, interviews, documentaries, and cultural performances from the 1970s to the 1990s. The recordings include several notable faculty members, visiting scholars, and activists, including Harold Cruse, Cornell West, Rita Dove, Jesse Jackson, Angela Davis, Marian Wright Edelman and Rosa Parks.
The audio-visual material in the collection is organized is organized in to six series by format: Audio recordings on cassettes, 1975-2001 (486 cassettes, 9 linear feet), U-Matic videotapes, 1971-1989 (91 videotapes, 9.1 linear ft.) VHS videotapes, 1971-2004 (131 videotapes, 7 linear feet), Open reel videotapes, 1971-1980 (12 videotapes, 1 linear feet), Reel-to-reel audiotape, 1971, 1980 and undated (4 audiotapes, 0.3 linear feet) and Mini DVDs, 1999-2000 and undated (24 Mini-DVDs, 0.2 linear feet).
African Americans -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; African Americans -- Study and teaching (Higher); Blacks -- Study and teaching.; Civil rights -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Divestment -- South Africa.; African Americans -- Michigan.; African Americans -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Digital audio files.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.; Digital file formats.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Ella Baker-Nelson Mandela Center for Anti-Raicst Education.; United Coalition Against Racism (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Center for Afroamerican and African Studies.; University of Michigan. Department of Afroamerican and African Studies.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Political activity.
- Black student activism, 1969-2001
  The series Black student activism, 1969-2001 (5.5 linear feet) contains four alphabetically arranged subseries relating to the Black Action Movements (BAM) on the University of Michigan campus: BAM I, 1969-1987 (0.4 linear feet), BAM II, 1974-1975 (0.1 linear feet), BAM III, 1985-1995 (0.5 linear feet) and Conferences and Scholarship about BAM, 1970-2001 (0.1 linear feet). These records include correspondence, newspaper clippings, minutes and other records of the United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR), and they address both the movements themselves and reactions to them within the university community. There are also documents concerning incidents of racial harassment that had a part in inspiring the movements.
  In 2014 the Bentley Historical Library digitized select archival records relating to BAM I, II and III housed in other University collections. Finding aid to Black Action Movement select documents, 1970-1987 digital collection is available online and contains links to the digitized files.
  A fifth subseries, Other activism,1966-2000 (3.9 linear feet), includes newspaper clippings about the civil rights movement; and the anti-apartheid and divestment movements of the 1980s, as well as records of several activist organizations, particularly the Free South Africa Coordinating Committee (FSACC), and the Washtenaw County Coalition Against Apartheid (WCCAA). Some of these records pertain to activities on campus, but most are concerned with political and civil rights causes that are national or international in scope. The Washtenaw County Coalition Against Apartheid (WCCAA) records document that organization's efforts to encourage the University of Michigan and Ann Arbor banks to divest their holdings in South Africa.
  More records relating to UCAR and the Baker -Mandela Center (BMC) are presented in the "Other activism" subseries, and pertain to activism and events at the University of Michigan during the 1980s and 1990s. Though UCAR and the BMC were separate entities, their records have been arranged together as a result of their frequent and close collaboration.
  Black Action Movement select documents, 1970-1987.
  - Black Action Movement I, 1969-1987
    - Black Action Movement (BAM), selected documents, 1970-1987 (Box 1)
      [Access to digitized content is enabled for the University of Michigan campus IP range and remote users who are able to authenticate via the University of Michigan weblogin.]
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971
      - Alumni, Opposition to the Strike, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Alumni, Support for the Strike, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Faculty, Incoming and Outgoing, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - President, Incoming and Outgoing, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - Regents (Box 1)
      - University Administrators, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Journal Articles Michigan Alumnus, Michigan Journal of Political Science, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Materials, 1970
      - BAM Key Negotiators, 1970 (Box 1)
      - BAM Position Statement on Negotiations, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, Incoming, Memos, Announcements, Outgoing, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Day 9 of Strike, Notes, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Demands, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Demands Not Met, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Edwin Farbe Speech to Enact Teach-In, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Flyers, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Daily Article, "The BAM Dispute" Draft, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Response to Demands, 1970
        - Community, Ann Arbor Tenants Union, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Faculty: Black Faculty, Residential College, School of Education, School of Public Health, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Regents, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Students, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Unidentified Group, 1970 (Box 1)
        - University, 1970 (Box 1)
        - University Staff: Teaching Fellows, AFSCME Local 1583 Psych Section 483 Outreach Staff, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970
      - Chicago Tribune, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Detroit Free Press, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Detroit News, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Indianapolis Star, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Daily, 1970; 1975 (Box 1)
      - Toledo Blade, 1970 (Box 1)
      - University Record, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Outcomes, 1969-1970
      - Academic Supportive Services Program, 1970 (Box 1)
      - BAM Position Statement on the Negotiations (Draft), 1970 (Box 1)
      - Black Student Center, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
      - Center for Afro-American Studies Proposal, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Disciplinary Hearings, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Minority Enrollment, Recruitment, and Financial Support, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) Resolution, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Student Publications, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement II, 1974-1975
    - Flyers, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings Michigan Daily, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement III, 1985-1995
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1985-1995
      - BAM Revival Ann Arbor News, Michigan Daily, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
      - BAM/UCAR Demands Ann Arbor News, Detroit Free Press, Michigan Daily, University Record, 1982; 1987 (Box 1)
      - Computer Bulletin Board Joke File Detroit Free Press, Michigan Daily, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Couzens Hall Flyer Ann Arbor News, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Death Threat Against UCAR Leader Michigan Daily, 1988 (Box 1)
      - Fragments, 1987-1988; Undated (Box 1)
      - General, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
      - Harassment Incident Michigan Daily, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Jesse Jackson, 1987 (Box 1)
      - LSA Dean Peter O. Steiner Resignation, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
      - Mandatory Course on Racism, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Mandate, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Mike Wallace Protest Ann Arbor News, Detroit Free Press, Michigan Daily, University Record, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Minority Enrollment Michigan Daily, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Minority Financial Aid Concerns, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - Morris Hood Hearings on Racism at U-M, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Mosher Jordan Flyer Michigan Daily, 1987 (Box 1)
      - President Harold Shapiro Resignation, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Protests, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Response to campus racism, 1988-1995
        - Faculty, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
        - General, 1987-1995; 5 folders (Box 1)
        - National, 1987-1988 (Box 55)
        - President, 1987 (Box 55)
        - Regents, 1987 (Box 55)
        - University Administration, 1987-1988 (Box 55)
      - Sanctions on Free Speech Michigan Daily, 1987-1988 (Box 55)
      - South Quad Macing Michigan Daily, 1991 (Box 55)
      - Special editions University Record, 1986-1987 (Box 55)
      - Student Code of Conduct Michigan Daily, 1987 (Box 55)
      - UCAR Ann Arbor News, Detroit Free Press, Michigan Daily, 1987-1988 (Box 55)
      - United Coalition Against Racism Conference Michigan Daily, 1989 (Box 55)
      - WJJX Broadcast of Racist Jokes, 1987 (Box 55)
    - United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR), 1987-1991
      - Committees List, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Conferences, 1987; 1989 (Box 55)
      - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 55)
      - Flyers, 1987-1991 (Box 55)
      - Hearing Procedures, Presidents Committee, Undated (Box 55)
      - Incident Documentation Form, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Mosher Jordan Racist Flyers Incident, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Newsletters, 1988-1990 (Box 55)
      - Petition Coordinator, Instruction Sheet, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Press Releases, 1987-1988 (Box 55)
      - Programs, Teach-in on Racism, etc., Undated (Box 55)
      - Proposal for LSA Course on Racism, 1990(?) (Box 55)
      - Proposals, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Racist Flyers at Couzens Hall, 1987 (Box 55)
      - Recommendations on Negotiated Agreements, 1987 (Box 55)
      - South Quad Macing Incident, 1990-1991 (Box 55)
      - Statement of Unity, 1987 (Box 55)
  - Conferences and scholarship about BAM, 1970-2001
    - A Decade after BAM, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Richard H. Ross, "Brief Chronological 'The History of the Negro American' Course (Black History Course) and the Early Stages of the Michigan Student Movement on Campus from 1966 to 1970", 1999; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The University Since BAM: Twenty Years of Progress (Includes Henry Vance Davis's paper "From Coloreds to African-Americans: A History of the Struggle for Educational Equity at the University of Michigan and an Agenda for the Pluralistic Multicultural University of the Twenty-first Century"), 1990 (Box 2)
    - W. Ellison Chalmers, "The University of Michigan and the Black Action Movement", 1970 (Box 2)
  - Other activism, 1966-2000
    - CAAS Library Black Student Activism Collection guides and collection maintenance, 1989-1999; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Organizations, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1992
      - Civil Rights Movement, 1966-1967; 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Civil Rights Movement and Vietnam War, 1967; 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Presidential Candidates, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Presidential Candidates, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
      - Riots, International,1987-1989 (Box 2)
      - Riots, United States, 1986-1989; 1992 (Box 2)
    - Political Prisoners in the United States, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Presidential Candidates, Rainbow Coalition, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Racial Incidents on University Campuses, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Soldiers and the Draft, Undated (Box 2)
    - South Africa and Apartheid, 1971-1990 (Box 2)
    - South Africa and Apartheid, Political Prisoner Bracelets, 1986-1990 (Box 2)